Guide to the John P. Watson papers,1946-1988.
Watson, John P. papers,1946-1988.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John P. Watson papers, 1946-1988.
22-3-3565
John P. Watson
4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The collection contains primarily correspondence files as well as course work materials that date from his undergraduate days at the University of Massachusetts, which awarded him a B. S. in 1948. Watson received his M. S. from Rutgers University in 1950.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
John P. Watson was a pomologist at the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station in the Department of Horticultural Sciences. His career as a fruit breeder at the Experiment Station in Geneva began in 1950. He worked with varieties of grape and plum for New York and the Northeastern United States. Watson was in charge of the care of seedling vineyards and assisted in planning and making crosses of potential grape varieties. During his 37 years at the Station, he was involved in the introduction of 17 varieties of grape, including Cayuga White, Einset Seedless, and Chardonel and the Iroquois, Seneca, Oneida, and Mohawk plums. In 1988, a new raspberry introduced by the Geneva Station was named Watson in his honor. Watson retired as a Senior Research Support Specialist in 1987, the year he was also named Most Outstanding Employee at the Experiment Station.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection contains primarily correspondence files as well as course work materials that date from his undergraduate days at the University of Massachusetts, which awarded him a B. S. in 1948. Watson received his M. S. from Rutgers University in 1950.
Also, subject files including plum varies.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wagner, Philip; Watson, John P.; Eastern Wine and Grape Archive.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Stateion--Horticultural Sciences.; New York State Department of Agriculture and Markets.; New York State Fruit Testing Cooperative Association, Inc.
Subjects:
Pomology--New York (State); Grape varieties--New York (State); Plum varieties--New York (State)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Forms part of the Eastern Wine and Grape Archive. (EWGA)
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Course Material
  - Course Work, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    University of Massachusetts, Horticulture and Botany (undergraduate)
  - Course Work, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    University of Massachusetts, Plant Breeding 51 (Undergraduate)
  - Pesticide Application-Certification, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Plums Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Prunes Correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Trickler Farm Plantings (Layout), 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: General Correspondence
  - A, 1962-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B, 1962-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C, 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - D, 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - E, 1965-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - F, 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - G, 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - H, 1962-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - I, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - J, 1969-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - K, 1965-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - L, 1967-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - M, Part 1, 1962-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - M, Part 2, 1977-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - N, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - O, 1962-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - P-Q, 1958-1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - R, 1963-1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - S, 1963-1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - T, 1966-1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - U, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - V, 1963-1986 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - W-X, 1960-1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Y, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Z, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence A-O, 1953-1962 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence P-Z, 1953-1962 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence I, 1939-1962 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence II, 1939-1951 (Box 3)
- Series III: Subject Files
  - Plum Records, 1959-1985 (Box 2)
    Concerning planting, plum propagation, and virus index.
  - General Notes, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    Regarding nursery records, nursery planting, and greenhouse propagation.
  - Miscellaneous, Variety Lists-Geneva 1954-1966 Weed Control 1977-1983 Open House 1982 Planning Committee 1983; 1954-1983 (Box 3)
  - Plum-Cooperations, Old-Inactive, Thomas Mark's Nursery 1941-1948 L.C. Anderson, Claverack, NY 1943-1947 Sigma XI 1940-1949 Spencer Lens Material 1941-1942 Minn. Plum and Pear Planting 1940; 1940-1949 (Box 3)
  - Data, Orchard Discards 1969 FTA 1968 Plum Progress Report 1965 Project Summaries 1960 Moving Data 1969 Greenhouse 1963-1964 Plum Variety Trial 1962; 1940-1969 (Box 3)
  - Reports, Plant Physiology 1950 Horticulture 1935-1946 Advanced Pomology-references 1950 Peach Genetics 1949 Apple Breeding 1954; 1935-1954 (Box 3)
  - Notebooks, Greenhouse 1980 Plum Correspondence 1940 Plums, etc. 1966 Greenhouse P + V 1981 Green notebook, has his wife's name, Judith Lambert, but is his writing on apples, berries, etc.. Also Department of Agriculture Visitor's Booklet, 1947. ca. 1950; 1940-1981 (Box 3)
  - Bulletins, NY Peach Bulletin 1946 Articles on Fruit Varieties NY Apricot Varieties + Rootstocks 1965 Balsgard, Nybum, Mutants, etc. 1968; 1946-1981 (Box 3)
  - Plant Breeding, Plant Breeding Class-Outlines 1978 Cornell Fruit Breeding Class Notes 1981-1984 Rutgers Advanced Breeding Course 1948-1949; 1948-1984 (Box 3)
  - Systematic Pomology, Sys. Pomology Description Sheets 1949-1978 Systematic 1949 Strawberry-Economics 1960-1989; 1947-1989 (Box 3)
  - Plums, 1959-1987 (Box 4)
    Includes plum propagation, IR-2 Repository papers, data lists of plum varieties, and general notes regarding canned plums, processing, planting, and spray data.
  - Pomology Progress Reports, 1957-1986 (Box 4)
    Covers plums, apricots, strawberries, blackberries and raspberries.
  - Plum Project Reports, 1948-1985 (Box 4)
    Includes project statements, progress reports, and notes/data regarding plum breeding.
  - Miscellaneous, 1953-1986 (Box 4)
    Includes USDA-plant inspection and permits, stone fruit bud distribution, IR-2, Tree Fruit Scion Available List, and data regarding peach varieties and Xiphinema.